A Guide to the Carter Family Shirley Plantation Records, 1736-1923
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carter Family Shirley Plantation Records, 1736-1923
Library of Virginia
28429
10 reels of microfilm.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Mr. and Mrs. C. Hill Carter, Jr., Shirley Plantation, Charles City County, Virginia, 8 March 1967, 1 June 1967, and 14 November 1974.
Biographical/Historical Information
Prominent planter family resident in Charles City County, Virginia. The family has continuously resided on the land of Shirley in Charles City County, Virginia, since 1660 when it was patented.
Scope and Content Information
Shirley Plantation records, 1736-1923, of the Carter family of Charles City County, Virginia, consisting of five series: Shirley Plantation Business Papers, 1812-1879; Shirley Plantation Records, 1736-1923; Shirley Plantation Records, 1815-1906; Shirley Plantation Records, 1840-1876; and Shirley Plantation Records, 1801-1879.
Shirley Plantation records, 1812-1879, consist of Hill Carter, Shirley Plantation business papers, 1816-1879; Hill Carter's account book with Wortham and McGruder, 1818-1875; tax notices and receipts, court fees, and militia fines; "Upper Shirley" papers, 1867-1875; Carter-Randolph family papers, 1821-1862; and family genealogies. Shirley Plantation records, 1736-1923, consist of: Shirley Plantation business papers, 1736-1874; William Fizthugh Carter of Upper Shirley papers, 1867-1885; Confederate bonds, 1861-1864; and Robert E. Lee receipts, 1836-1845. Shirley Plantation records, 1815-1906, consist of: naval journal from aboard the USS Peacock in 1815; cruise journal from the USS Falmouth, 1842-1843; Robert R. Carter letter book, 1866-1887; Robert R. Carter account books, 1856-1899; Shirley notebook, 1866-1887 (1937); Shirley farm journal, 1872-1874 and 1882-1887; Marion Carter diary, 1878-1885; Louise Humphreys Carter Diaries, 1884-1889 and 1903-1906; Shirley slave record book, 1853-1864; Hill Carter cash account books, 1819-1875. Shirley Plantation records, 1840-1876, include: Shirley Plantation business records, 1858-1876; Carter-Randolph legal papers, 1862-1875; nad Hill Carter legal papers, 1855-1874. Shirley Plantation records, 1801-1879, include: Robert Carter diary, 1801; Hill Carter account book, 1816-1848; Shirley account book, 1816-1879; Shirley journal, 1822-1824; Hill Carter hirelings account books, 1822-1846 and 1866-1870; Hill Carter, memorandum books, 1842-1847 and 1850-1853; and Hill Carter, bank account books, 1819-1872.
Arrangement and Organization
The arrangement is more or less chronological within each group, except for the group headed "Genealogy."
Organized into the following five series: Series I. Shirley Plantation business records, 1812-1879. Series II. Shirley Plantation records, 1736-1923. Series III. Shirley Plantation records, 1815-1906. Series IV. Shirley Plantation records, 1840-1876. Series V. Shirley Plantation records, 1801-1879.
Originals
Originals are now located at Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, P.O. Box 1776, Williamsburg, VA 23187-1776.
Contents List
- Shirley Plantation Records, 1812-1879 (Reel 1-5)
  - Shirley Plantation Business Papers, 1812-1879 (Reel 1-4)
    - Hill Carter, Shirley Plantation Business Papers, 1816-1830 (Reel 1)
    - Hill Carter, Shirley Plantation Business Papers, 1831-1848 (Reel 2)
    - Hill Carter, Shirley Plantation Business Papers, 1849-1869 (Reel 3)
    - Hill Carter, Shirley Plantation Business Papers, 1870-1879 (Reel 4)
    - Hill Carter, in Account with Wortham & McGruder, 1818-1875 (Reel 4)
    - Tax Notices and Receipts, Court Fees, Militia Fines, 1812-1873 (Reel 4)
    - "Upper Shirley" Papers, 1867-1875 (Reel 4)
  - Carter-Randolph Family Papers, 1821-1862 (Reel 4)
    - In Suit, Landonia J. Randolph v. Ann C. Kincaid, 1853-1860 (Reel 4)
    - Norwood Estate Papers, 1840-1862 (Reel 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1820-1829 (Reel 4)
  - Genealogy (Reel 5)
    - Genealogy, Memorabilia (Reel 5)
    - Correspondence, Memorabilia, 1846-1923 (Reel 5)
    - Carter Family Correspondence, 1840-1885 (Reel 5)
- Shirley Plantation Records, 1736-1885 (Reel 6)
  - Shirley Plantation Business Papers, 1736-1874 (Reel 6)
  - William Fitzhugh Carter, Upper Shirley, 1867-1885 (Reel 6)
  - Confederate Bonds, 1861-1864 (Reel 6)
  - Robert E. Lee, receipts, 1836-1845 (Reel 6)
- Shirley Plantation Records, 1815-1906 (Reel 7-9)
  - Naval Journal, USS Peacock, 24 January 1815-19 July 1815 (Reel 7)
  - Journal of a Cruise, USS Falmouth, 1842-1843 (Reel 7)
  - Robert R. Carter, Letterbook, 1866-1887 (Reel 7)
  - Robert R. Carter, Account Book, 1856-1858, 1878-1899 (Reel 7)
  - Robert R. Carter, Account Book; Westover Parish Account Book (Ledger), 1858-1869 (Reel 7)
  - Robert R. Carter, Shirley Account Book, 1866-1877 (Reel 7)
  - Shirley Notebook, 1866-1887 (1937) (Reel 7)
  - Shirley Farm Journal, 1872-1874, 1882-1887 (Reel 8)
  - Charles Carter, Farm Journal, 1880-1889 (Reel 8)
  - [Marion Carter] Diary, 1878-1885 (1942) (Reel 8)
  - Louise H[umphreys] Carter Diary, 1884-1889 (Reel 8)
  - [Louise Humphreys Carter] Diary, 1903-1906 (Reel 8)
  - Shirley, Slave Record Book, 1853-1864 (Reel 8)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1819-1821 (Reel 8)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1821-1824 (Reel 8)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1824-1827 (Reel 8)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1827-1832 (Reel 8)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1832-1837 (Reel 8)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1837-1846 (Reel 8)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1846-1857 (Reel 9)
  - Hill Carter, Cash Account Book, 1857-1875 (Reel 9)
- Shirley Plantation Records, 1855-1876 (Reel 10)
  - Shirley Plantation Business Records, 1858-1876 (Reel 10)
  - Carter-Randolph Legal Papers, 1862-1875 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter Legal Papers, 1855-1874 (Reel 10)
- Shirley Plantation Records, 1801-1879 (Reel 10)
  - Robert Carter Diary, Philadelphia, 1801 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Account Book, 1816-1848 (Reel 10)
  - Shirley Account Book, 1816-1879 (Reel 10)
  - Shirley Journal, 1822-1824 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Hirelings Account Book, 1822-1846 (Reel 10)
  - Shirley, Hirelings Account Book, 1866-1870 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Memorandum Books, 1842-1847, 1850-1853 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Bank Account Book, 1819 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Bank Account Book, 1821-1823 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Bank Account Book, 1833-1850 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Bank Account Book, 1841-1848 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Bank Account Book, 1843-1860 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Bank Account Book, 1849-1864 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, Bank Account Book, 1851-1864 (Reel 10)
  - Hill Carter, (trustee), Bank Account Book, 1871-1872 (Reel 10)